Guide to the Special Collections Research Center oral history collection, 1972-2016 MS0371
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- George Washington University oral histories, 1974-; Series 2; 7.75 Linear Feet 7 full and 1 partial document boxes, 1 slim document box, 2 partial records center cartons, 4 partial tape boxes, and numerous digital recordings and transcription files
  - Bernard Svedlow and Gerry Svedlow interviewed by David Anderson, 1991 October 4; 5 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 33, Cassette 34, Cassette 35, Box 7, Cassette 1, Cassette 2)
    Interview is closed due to lack of releases signed by either Svedlows.
  - Francine Zorn Trachtenberg interviews (Box R4)
    Interviews are closed due to lack of a signed release from Trachtenberg.
    Consists of transcripts and digital recordings of two interviews conducted with Francine Zorn Trachtenberg in 2009.
  - GW President Stephen Trachtenberg interviews upon retirement, 2008 (Box R4)
    The interview was closed until January 1, 2022. It is open now for researchers.
    Consists of transcripts and digital recordings of a series of 8 interviews conducted with Stephen Joel Trachtenberg at the end of his term as president of George Washington University.
  - GW Vibes oral histories, 2016; 14 digital object(s)
    Final paper and video oral histories completed with members of the GW Vibes acapella group by student Kirin Dombek as part of Prof. Lornell's ethnomusicology class. Includes releases for the oral histories.
    Accession 2016.077
  - Harry Wallerstein interviewed by G. David Anderson, 1992 February 4; 6 Cassettes 3 copies of 2 cassettes each; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 7, Cassette 15, Cassette 16, Cassette 17, Cassette 18, Cassette 19, Cassette 20)
  - Winfield Weitzel interviewed by David Anderson, 1989 November 14; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 7, Cassette 21)
  - Dr. Youtha Hardman-Cromwell interviewed by Phillip Troutman, 2018; Series 2
    General
    Professor Troutman and students in his class interviewed Dr. Hardman-Cromwell.
    Dr. Youtha Hardman-Cromwell came to GW as a student in August 1958.
    Interview is open for research.
- Medical Center Oral History Committee, 1972-1988; Series 3; 1.5 Linear Feet 1 whole and 3 partial cassette tape boxes, and 2 document boxes
  Some interviews in this series are closed due to a lack of signed releases from the interviewees. These restrictions are noted at the item-level.
  Transferred to the archives by Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library in 2003. Formerly ACC#1054
  Physically, the materials for a single interview (e.g., cassette tapes, administrative file, and transcript) are spread across multiple boxes because they are stored according to format. Transcripts and files for interviews that are currently closed have been moved to boxes whose numbers begin with an "R", although the recordings continue to be stored alongside those for open interviews.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains records and oral history interviews from the Medical Center Oral History Project undertaken in the 1970s and 1980s. The interviews were done with faculty, staff and alumni of the GW Medical Center. Some of the individuals interviewed by this project were also interviewed by the university archives' oral history program, so may have interviews in both series.
  - Oral history committee records, 1972-1984 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Recordings of oral history committee meetings, 1980-1981; 5 Cassettes 2 possible duplicates (Box 7)
  - Dr. Seymour Alpert interviewed by Dr. Thomas M. Peery, 1978; 1 folder(s); 4 Cassettes 2 copies of 2 cassettes each (Box R3, Box 5)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Alpert.
  - Dr. Walter Bloedorn interviewed by Dr. Thomas M. Peery, 1977 June 8; 1 folder(s); 10 Cassettes 10 masters, 4 copies (Box R3, Box 8)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Bloedorn
  - Catherine Breen interviewed by Suzanne Grefsheim, 1983 March 22; 1 folder(s); 2 Cassettes (Box R3, Box 7)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Breen.
    Catherine Breen came to the George Washington University Medical School as assistant librarian and secretary for the Dean's office in 1924 and retired in the early 1970s.
  - Dr. Charles S. Coakley interviewed by Dr. Seymour Alpert, 1984 May 14; 2 folder(s); 1 Cassettes (Box 20, Box 8)
  - Dr. Clayton Ethridge interviewed by Dr. Thomas M. Peery, 1977 June 30; 2 folder(s); 2 Cassettes (Box R3, Box 5)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Ethridge.
  - Dr. Thelma Hunt interviewed by Dr. James Watts, 1984 July 9; 2 folder(s); 6 Cassettes 3 possible duplicates (Box 20, Box 8)
  - Dr. Sidney A. Levine interviewed Dr. Seymour Alpert, 1981 May 22; 2 folder(s); 2 Cassettes (Box 20, Box 5)
  - Victor Ludewig interviewed by Dr. Thomas M. Peery, 1981 July 15-16; 1 folder(s); 6 Cassettes 3 masters, 3 copies (Box R3, Box 8)
    Ludewig was chief administrator of the George Washi8ngton University Hospital from 1949 to 1973.
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Ludewig.
  - Nina W. Matheson interviewed by Suzanne Grefsheim, 1983 April 18; 1 folder(s); 3 Cassettes (Box 20, Box 8)
    Release signed by Matheson indicates that public access to the interview is "subject to review and approval of the transcript." There is no transcript available, and no evidence of whether this review and approval process occurred.
    Nina W. Matheson was director of the Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library beginning in 1974.
  - B. Oliphant interview, around 1979; 2 Cassettes (Box 7)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Oliphant.
  - Dr. Richard E. Palmer interviewed by Dr. Thomas M. Peery, 1978; 2 folder(s); 4 Cassettes 2 masters, 2 copies (Box R3, Box 5)
    Palmer is an alumnus of the George Washington University Medical School; he began in 1941.
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Palmer
  - Dr. John Parks interviewed by Roy Hoopes, around 1970; 2 folder(s); 3 Cassettes (Box R3, Box 8)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Parks
  - Dr. Thomas M. Peery interviewed by Dr. James Watts, 1979 February 12; 3 folder(s); 12 Cassettes 6 possible duplicates (Box 20, Box R3, Box 8)
    One folder containing a transcript of "supplementary material deleted from interview" with Dr. Peery is closed to research. This folder has been removed to box R3.
  - Dr. Mary Louise Robbins interviewed by Louis Affronti, 1978 November 6; 2 folder(s); 2 Cassettes 1 master, 1 copy (Box R3, Box 5)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Robbins
  - Dr. Ira Rockwood Telford interviewed by Frank D. Allan, 1978 June 6; 1 folder(s); 2 Cassettes 1 master, 1 copy (Box R3, Box 8)
    From 1954 to 1972, Telford was a professor and chairman of the department of anatomy at George Washington University.
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Telford
  - Dr. James W. Watts interviewed by Dr. Thomas M. Peery, 1979 January 25; 2 folder(s); 12 Cassettes 6 masters, 6 copies (Box 20, Box 7, Box 8)
  - Dr. James W. Watts interviewed regarding the use of his collection, around 1980; 1 Cassettes (Box 8)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Watts. No transcript exists.
  - Isabella F. Young interviewed by Suzanne Grefsheim, 1983 March 10; 1 folder(s); 2 Cassettes (Box R3, Box 8)
    Isabella Young was librarian at the George Washington University Medical School from 1931 to 1945 and from 1952 until her retirement in 1971.
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Young.
  - Members of the department of surgery interviewed as a group by Dr. Thomas M. Peery, 1988 April 19; 1 folder(s); 8 Cassettes 4 masters, 4 copies (Box R3, Box 6)
    The interview included Dr. James Winston Watts, Dr. Vincent Michael Iovine, and Dr. Howard Pierpont
    The interview is closed due to lack of releases signed by the participants
  - Members of the GW University Hospital Women's Board interviewed as a group by Etta Richwine, 1981 February 11; 1 folder(s); 8 Cassettes 4 possible duplicates (Box R3, Box 7)
    Participants in the interview were Mrs. Barton Richwine, Mrs. S. Hazen-Bond, Mrs. Samuel McElroy Burgess, Mrs. Joseph Roe, Mrs. Benjamin D. VanEvra, and Mrs. Alvin Parrish. Mrs. S. Laszlo Sommer and Mrs. John Parks also contributed to the interview.
    Interview is closed due to lack of signed releases from the participants
- Foggy Bottom oral histories, 1977, 1995-1997, 2011, 2013; Series 4; 0.5 Linear Feet 3 partial cassette tape boxes, 2 partial records center cartons, and digital recordings.
  Physically, the materials for a single interview (e.g., cassette tapes, reel-to-reel tape, and transcript) are spread across multiple boxes because they are stored according to format.
  GW has undertaken at least three distinct oral history projects with long-time residents of Foggy Bottom. The first was a small number of interviews done on behalf of the Oral History Program in the 1970s. Then, in the late 1990s, the university archives conducted a series of interviews as an outgrowth of a 1996 exhibit sponsored by the Foggy Bottom Association and the Gelman Library called "Fantastic Foggy Bottom: The Growth of a Community," which was designed in conjunction with GW's 175th Anniversary. Interviews from both of these efforts exist as cassette recordings, some reel-to-reel recordings, and transcripts.
  In 2012, as part of the 100th anniversary of GW's presence in the Foggy Bottom neighborhood, another oral history project was conducted by GW Assistant Vice President for DC Relations Bernard Demczuk and GW graduate student Katherine Mead. These interviews exist solely as digital recordings.
  This series also contains digital files of oral history recordings and transcripts created by undergraduate students in the GW history course HIST2020W, "Washington, DC: History, Culture, and Politics," taught by Dr. Christopher Klemek, who interviewed former and current residents of Foggy Bottom and Southwest neighborhoods.
  - George Arnstein interview and transcript, 2013 April 12; Series 5 Sub-series 1; 2 digital object(s)
    This interview was conducted by undergraduate students in the GW history course HIST2020W, "Washington, DC: History, Culture, and Politics," taught by Christopher Klemek.
  - George Bozzini interview and transcript, 2013 April 20; 7 digital object(s)
  - Mary Brown interviewed by by Laetitia Combrinck, 1997 June 3; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 5, Cassette 15)
  - Mary Brown interviewed by Bernard Demczuk and Katherine Mead, 2011 December 11
  - Dan Grossman interview and transcript, 2013 April 12; 2 digital object(s)
  - Hazel Hanback interviewed by David Anderson, 1995 May 19; 1 folder(s); 1 Cassettes (Box 16, Box 6, Cassette 28)
  - Hazel Hanback interviewed by David Anderson, 1996 October 28; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 6, Cassette 29, Cassette 30)
  - Hazel Hanback interviewed by David Anderson, 1996 November 19; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 5, Cassette 30)
  - Alameda Hanesborough and Bradford A. Tatum interviewed by Bernard Demczuk and Katherine Mead, 2011 December 16
  - Eric Marlow interviewed by Letitia Combrinck, 1997 August 18; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 6, Cassette 15, Cassette 16)
  - Ira Miles interviewed by Dana Perry, 1977 June; 1 Cassettes (Box 3, Cassette 38)
    Discussion of the Washington D.C. area just above Foggy Bottom
  - Alfred Montgomery interviewed by Bernard Demczuk and Katherine Mead, 2011 December 16
  - Inez Elizabeth Murray interviewed by Bernard Demczuk and Katherine Mead, 2011 December 12
  - Ethel Perritt interviewed by Dana Perry, 1977 June (Box 3, Cassette 39)
    Discussion of Perritt's childhood in the Foggy Bottom area of Washington, D.C., especially recalling area churches, schools, drugstores, etc.
  - McKenzie "Mac" Perritt interviewed by Dana Perry, 1977 June (Box 3, Cassette 40)
    Discussion of the Foggy Bottom area in the early half of the twentieth century. Comments on Briggs Elementary School and major buildings and industries in Foggy Bottom during his childhood.
  - Daisy Sewell interviewed by Bernard Demczuk and Katherine Mead, 2011 December 12
  - Mattie Shippen interviewed by Dana Perry, 1977 June 15; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 1, Reel 14, Side 2, Box 3, Cassette 41)
    Discussion of the importance of St. Mary's Church in the community of Foggy Bottom; role of the last principal of the St. Mary's sewing school
  - Alex Radin interview and transcript, 2013 April 23; 2 digital object(s)
  - Carol Radin interview and transcript, 2013 April 10; 2 digital object(s)
  - Ruth M. Reed, Alameda Hanesborough, Mary Brown, and Daisy Sewell interviewed by Bernard Demczuk and Katherine Mead, 2012 January 22
  - Wilmer David Riley and James L. Briscoe interviewed by Bernard Demczuk and Katherine Mead, 2011 December 5; 2 digital object(s)
    James L. Briscoe was president of Old Georgetown Foggy Bottom Inc.
  - Kathleen Snyder interview and transcript, 2013 April 11; 2 digital object(s)
  - Leonard Teitelbaum interviewed by Laetitia Combrinck, 1997 June 10; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 7, Cassette 3)
  - Jack Warner interview and transcript, 2013 April 12; 2 digital object(s)
- Miscellaneous oral histories and administrative files, 1972-1981, 1998, 2002; Series 5; 1 Linear Feet 1 partial document box, 3 partial cassette tape boxes, and 3 partial record center cartons
  This series is arranged intellectually by subject, with those subjects for which there are multiple interviews being listed first, and one-off interviews arranged alphabetically by interviewee name after that.
  This series consists of oral histories and administrative files from the Oral History Program under Mary Jo Deering's direction which do not fit in other categories in this collection. These oral histories appear to have been done either as an exploration of a potential area for an oral history project, or as student projects. Major topics include fair housing programs and the performing arts in DC.
  This series also contains interviews related to other collections in Special Collections, specifically interviews with Walter Fauntroy and Ari and Phyllis Kiev.
  - Oral history program admininstrative files, around 1972-1981 (Box 16)
    Includes program reports, plans, and the finding aid for the original oral history collection.
  - Housing: Morris Milgram interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1976 July 21; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 15, Box 7, Cassette 33, Cassette 34)
    Milgram's pioneering involvement in integrated housing, neighborhoods, and apartment complexes on the East Coast and especially in Montgomery County, Maryland. Also, the National Committee on Tithing in Investment and National Neighbors, an organization of integrated neighborhood associations. Fair housing laws.
  - Housing: Joyce B. Siegel interviewed by Margaret Cutler, 1976 October 18 (Box 15)
    Background of black community of Scotland in the Bethesda-Potomac area of Montgomery County, Maryland. Origins and progress of plans to upgrade housing conditions and create community organizations capable of controlling local decisions.
  - Background documents related to housing discrimination, around 1976 (Box 15)
    Documents apparently gathered in preparation for interviewing Milgram and Siegel about housing discrimination.
  - Performing Arts in Washington: Frankie Hewitt interviewed by Linda Beattie, 1977 June 16; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s); 2 digital object(s) (Box R1, Box 7, Cassette 35)
    The Director of Ford's Theater discusses its origins and the origins of the Ford's Theater Society since the theater's restoration in 1968.
    Interview is closed due to no release having been obtained from Hewitt.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    The original audio cassette is very fragile and should not be used. A digital surrogate is available.
  - Performing Arts in Washington: Nancy Pittman interviewed by Pamela Henson, 1977 June; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 3, Cassette 35, Cassette 36)
    Discussion of City Dance '77 and the Washington Performing Arts Society
  - Performing Arts in Washington: Catherine Shouse interviewed by Roberta Greene, 1977 March 11 (Box R1)
    Interview is closed due to lack of release from Shouse
    Origins of the Wolf Trap bequest
  - Performing Arts in Washington: Douglas Wheeler interviewed by Pamela Henson, 1977 June (Box 16, Box 3, Cassette 37)
    Discussion on the development of the idea of a Washington, D.C. dance festival, City Dance '77, and the Washington Performing Arts Society
  - Performing Arts in Washington: Research and planning files on a potential Wolf Trap oral history project, approximately 1977; 2 folder(s) (Box 16)
  - Fernando Belaunde-Terry interviewed by Cynthia Stout, 1977 April 21 - 1978 April 11; 7 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 4, Cassette 34, Cassette 35, Cassette 36, Cassette 37, Cassette 38, Cassette 39, Cassette 40)
    Reminiscences of the former president of Peru (1963-1968): childhood, career as an architect, political involvement in Peru, presidency, overthrow, future plans.
  - Mimi Conway interview, 1981; 1 Cassettes (Box R2)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Conway.
    Interview of Mimi Conway by an unidentified man and woman; subject is the research behind her book Rise Gonna Rise: A Portrait of Southern Textile Workers.
  - Rev. Walter Fauntroy interviewed by Michelle Stewert, 1998 April 28; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 7, Cassette 23)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Fauntroy.
  - Lyn Goldfarb interviewed by Jeneane Johanningmeier, 1977 April 1 (Box 16)
    Discussion of the Women's Labor History Film Project; fund-raising techniques and project organization
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1979 July 2; 1.5 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 7, Cassette 6, Side B)
    Interview closed because no release signed from Kayser for this interview.
    Discussion of Kayser's current project about the downtown area of Washington, D.C.
  - Ari Kiev and Phyllis Kiev interviewed by Alice Stempler, 2002 December 22; 1 folder(s); 2 Cassettes (Box 16, Box 7, Cassette 29, Cassette 28)
    Interview is regarding Ari Kiev's father, Rabbi I. Edward Kiev.
  - Francis Lethbridge interviewed by Julie Koczela, 1979 June 22; 0.5 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 6, Side A)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Lethbridge.
    The architect is interviewed about development in the downtown area of Washington, D.C.
  - Alfred Baker Louis interviewed by Rhoda M. Durkan, 1974 March 28 (Box 16)
    Reminiscences of the then-National Treasurer Emeritus of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP); civil rights activities and political activities as a Socialist
  - M. Denis de Rougemont interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1974 March 14; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 17, Reel 11)
    Oral history interview in French with M. Denis de Rougemont Swiss author, Director of the Centre europeen de la Culture, Geneva, Switzerland. Topics include origins of various European activist groups in the 1930s, and during and after WWII; Congress of Motreaux (1947) and the Haugh (1948); creation of the European Cultural Center; Winston Churchill and the European movement.
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release form.